Guide to the Winifred Smith Papers, 1904-1959
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Winifred Smith Papers
1904-1959
Smith, Winifred, 1879-
3.8 cubic feet (15 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Materials relating to Smith's life and work in the Drama Department of Vassar College.
Biographical Note
Winifred Smith (1897-1967) was born in Cincinnati, Ohio. She was the daughter of Henry Preserved Smith, a leading Biblical scholar, and the sister of Preserved Smith, noted historian of the Reformation. After graduating from Vassar in 1904 and spending a year as a tutor at Mt. Holyoke College, and a year of student at the Sorbonne, Winifred Smith earned a Ph.D. from Columbia University in 1912.
In 1911 Miss Smith came to Vassar as an instructor in English, rising to the rank of professor. In 1916 she started a theatrical museum at Vassar and, with Emmeline Moore, a Shakespeare Garden to commemorate the 300th anniversary of Shakespeare’s birth. Winifred Smith's scholarly interest was in dramatic literature. She wrote books on The Commedia dell-Arte and Italian Actors in the Renaissance and numerous articles and reviews for periodicals such as The Nation and The Dial. She also translated many futurist plays from the French and Italian. When the Division of Drama was organized in 1938, she became its chairman, working closely with Hallie Flanagan Davis during the years of the Experimental Theatre.
Professor Smith was also active in the suffrage movement and participated in local civic activities, including the Community Theatre, the Women’s City and County Club, and the Citizens Better Housing League. She was the first president of the Dutchess County local of the American Federation of Teachers. She was interested in such social issues as disarmament and child labor.
Her retirement in 1947 was marked by an only slightly slower pace in a career outstanding for her willingness to act on a broad range of social concerns and scholarly interests. In a faculty memorial minute, Winifred Smith was named "one of Vassar’s great teachers” and “one of its great rebels." She had an adopted daughter, Ann Veronka, who graduated from Vassar in 1938.
Scope and Content Note
Papers include letters received regarding her books, fellowships, teaching and research opportunities, and other professional concerns; manuscripts on life at Vassar College, review of Vassar theater presentation, articles on plays and literature, and a lecture on the "Usefulness of Brains;" copies of her publications; Vassar reading lists and assignments; and a copy of a Vassar senior thesis by Mary Arnold Sykes, 1946. Also includes a card file of descriptions of college as well as local productions and notes on Vassar classes and curricula.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Sykes, Mary Arnold
Organizations:
Vassar College--Faculty; Vassar College--Students
Subjects:
Literature--Study and teaching; English language--Study and teaching; Women's colleges--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Drama--Study and teaching; Literature--Research; Women--Suffrage; Women college students--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Books and reading; Women--Social conditions; Women college teachers
VCL Categories
Literature and Writing; Theater, Drama and Film; Vassar College
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, April 2007.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Priscilla Smith Robertson (VC 1930) and other donors. Card file transfered from VC Drama Department in 2007 (M2007-015)
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence, (Boxes 15)
- Series II. Biographical Materials, (Box 15)
- Series III. Manuscripts and Published Works of Winifred Smith, (Box 15)
- Series IV. Vassar Related Materials, (Box 15)
- Series V. Drama Card File, (Boxes 1-14)
Container List
- Correspondence
  - Winifred Smith to Parents, 1892-1918 (Folder 15.1)
  - Winifred Smith to Parents, Jan-Mar 1921 (Folder 15.2)
  - Winifred Smith to Parents, April 1921 (Folder 15.3)
  - Winifred Smith to Parents, May-June 1921 (Folder 15.4)
  - Winifred Smith to Parents, July 1921 (Folder 15.5)
  - Winifred Smith to Parents, Aug-Dec 1921 (Folder 15.6)
  - Winifred Smith to Parents, 1922 (Folder 15.7)
  - Winifred Smith to Parents, Jan-May 1923 (Folder 15.8)
  - Winifred Smith to Parents, June-Dec 1923 (Folder 15.9)
  - Winifred Smith to Parents, 1924-1925 (Folder 15.10)
  - Winifred Smith to Parents, 1937 (Folder 15.11)
  - Winifred Smith to Parents, n.d. and fragments (Folder 15.12)
  - Winifred Smith to Agnes [a cousin], 1892 (Folder 15.13)
  - Winifred Smith to others, 1894-1949 (Folder 15.14)
  - Correspondence to Winifred Smith, 1904-1929 (Folder 15.15)
  - Correspondence to Winifred Smith, 1930-1959 (Folder 15.16)
  - Correspondence to Winifred Smith, 1944; oversized (Folder 15.16a)
  - Correspondence to Winifred Smith (Folder 15.17)
  - Correspondence re: Associated Alumnae Fellowship, 1908-1910 (Folder 15.18)
  - Correspondence from others to others, 1916-1929 (Folder 15.19)
- Biographical Materials
  - Miscellaneous biographical materials (Folder 15.19)
  - Memorial minute for Winifred Smith, read at Vassar College Faculty Meeting, 10 April 1968 (Folder 15.20)
  - Deed for 3 Randolph Avenue, Poughkeepsie, 1913 (Folder 15.21)
  - Photographs (Folder 15.22)
  - Clippings - Biographical (Folder 15.23)
  - Clippings – Obituaries, 1967 (Folder 15.24)
  - V.C. Press releases re: Winifred Smith, 1941-1967 (Folder 15.25)
  - Ephemera from Winifred Smith’s European trips (Folder 15.26)
  - Miscellaneous items (Folder 15.27)
- Manuscripts and Published Works of Winifred Smith
  - Antigone, 1918 (Folder 15.27a)
  - The Arabian Nights, 1911 (Folder 15.28)
  - Bernard Shaw and His Critics, 1892-1938, 1941 (Folder 15.29)
  - Cocteau’s Infernal Machines, n.d. (Folder 15.30)
  - Creon, Acts II-V, n.d. (Folder 15.31)
  - Four Greek heroines in Modern Dress (Folder 15.32)
  - Havelock the Dane, n.d. (Folder 15.33)
  - The Humorous Duke of As You Like It, 1915 (Folder 15.34)
  - Kurt, n.d. (Folder 15.35)
  - Mystics in the Modern Theatre, 1942 (Folder 15.36)
  - Nazi Drama and Its Roots (Folder 15.37)
  - Our Natacha, by Casona. Translated by Winifred Smith, 1936 (Folder 15.38)
  - The Problem Play and Comedy (Folder 15.39)
  - Right You Are! (If You Think So), n.d. (Folder 15.40)
  - Six Characters in Search of an Author, by Pirandello. Translated of Italian stage directions by Winifred Smith (Folder 15.41)
  - Six Characters... translated of Preface by Winifred Smith, n.d. (Folder 15.42)
  - Six Characters... translated of Preface by Winifred Smith, n.d. (Folder 15.43)
  - "The Usefulness of Brains" [Phi Beta Kappa Lecture] with commentary on speech in Vassar Miscellany and Vassar Chronicle, 1952 (Folder 15.44)
  - When I Entered Vassar..., n.d. (Folder 15.45)
  - Printed publications of Winifred Smith (Folder 15.46)
  - Printed publications of Winifred Smith (Folder 15.47)
  - Printed publications of Winifred Smith (Folder 15.48)
  - Printed publications of Winifred Smith (Folder 15.49)
  - Reviews of and references to Winifred Smith’s “The Commedia dell’ Arte,”, 1912 (Folder 15.50)
  - Book reviews by Winifred Smith (Folder 15.51)
  - Book reviews by Winifred Smith (Folder 15.52)
  - “Erasmus, Enemy of Pedantry,” by Preserved Smith, brother of Winifred Smith, n.d. (Folder 15.53)
- Vassar Related Materials
  - Reading lists and assignments, 1940-1944 (Folder 15.54)
  - Teaching notes (Folder 15.55)
  - Senior thesis, by Mary Arnold Sykes (VC 1946) (Folder 15.56)
- Drama Card File
  - "Russian Drama" (Box 1)
  - "U.S.A. & its drama, Melodrama, 18th & 19th c. Federal Theatre, Irish Theatre" (Box 1-2)
  - "German Drama, Modern" (Box 2-3)
  - "Shaw and background" (Box 3-4)
  - "Scandinavian, Spanish, Dutch, Czech, Irish Drama & G.B.S. Life" (Box 4)
  - [Shaw, Italian Literature and Theater] (Box 4-5)
  - "French Drama, Medieval 16th, 17th, 18th, 19th c." (Box 5)
  - "French Drama – Modern" (Box 5-6)
  - "English Drama – Modern" (Box 6-7)
  - "Greek Drama, Comedy, Tragedy, Criticism" (Box 7)
  - "Italian Drama (1500-1600), Actors, Theatres, Scenery, Masks" (Box 8)
  - "American Drama (l-w)" (Box 8-9)
  - "19th & 20th c. Theatre, Movies" (Box 9-10)
  - "Modern Drama, Background, science, philosophy, psychology, social life" (Box 10)
  - "Modern Drama (Don Juan), Theories, Style, Background (aesthetic), Poetry" (Box 10-11)
  - "19th Century Drama (early through Strindberg)" (Box 11-12)
  - "American Drama (a-k)" (Box 12-13)
  - "Italian Drama, Modern" (Box 13)
  - "Modern Plays, Bibliography, Theme, Pageantry groups, Marionettes, Capeks – Molnar, Munk & Dutch, Holberg" (Box 13-14)
  - "Aesthetics & Poetics, Epic, Comedy – Burlesque, Tragedy (classical), Pantamine" (Box 14)